<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-05-16T13:50:29+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Maahir Panchal</title><subtitle>A blog about technology and stuff related</subtitle><entry><title type="html">👨🏻‍💻 Updates on the Backend</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/updates-on-backend/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="👨🏻‍💻 Updates on the Backend" /><published>2021-04-26T20:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2021-04-26T20:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/updates-on-backend</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/updates-on-backend/">&lt;p&gt;For the past couple of days I’ve been messing around with the static site-generator Jekyll based on Ruby which is what I’ve used to make this website. It’s a pretty simple tool to use [I do have experience with coding] however I’ve been looking at workflows where people without a coding background can use this system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make this website I used &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; + &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; Pages and the Jekyll theme A.P by kssim. Now I’ll be adding &lt;a href=&quot;http://forestry.io&quot;&gt;Forestry&lt;/a&gt; to this workflow as my Content Management System or CMS. Now that takes care of my website structure, hosting and CMS. All I require now is to get a domain to host this which I’ve been procrastinating on for quite some time.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>johndoe</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="updates" /><summary type="html">For the past couple of days I’ve been messing around with the static site-generator Jekyll based on Ruby which is what I’ve used to make this website. It’s a pretty simple tool to use [I do have experience with coding] however I’ve been looking at workflows where people without a coding background can use this system.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/markdown.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/markdown.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">⚙️ Post 12th Grade: The Indian Engineering Scenario</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/post-12th-grade/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="⚙️ Post 12th Grade: The Indian Engineering Scenario" /><published>2021-03-08T20:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2021-03-08T20:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/post-12th-grade</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/post-12th-grade/">&lt;p&gt;The Indian engineering scene is weird. A lot of teens are forced into this line by peer and parental pressure. You may even have chosen it because you felt “this was it”. &lt;strong&gt;That&lt;/strong&gt; was probably due to lack of perspective [ More on this later ]. You enter a typical engineering college and see people frantically working towards makeshift end goals that bring no joy to them in the long run. It is the assignments and the tests and that project your teacher once suggested. The cramming of formulae that are not even used to solve a mathematical question but rather to be put in your paper for that guaranteed 1 mark. The Viva where you duel with your enemy i.e the professor you foulmouthed in class or bunked their lecture in front of them a couple of times. Don’t get me wrong, if &lt;strong&gt;This&lt;/strong&gt; is for you who am I to judge? However, for most students there are better careers in finance, marketing, advertising, accounting, video production, photography, music and this is just the tip of the iceberg.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So you got in an engineering college, what do you do now? Do you try to break free from the paradigm or do you fit in?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s get this straight. You are studying for a higher education degree because you want to learn. Your course will probably give you some sort of exposure regarding the stream you are in. That, in life, is not enough. You need to get the most out of the time you have. Learn life skills. Learning how to communicate with your peers and managing your time are some of the key lessons you learn in the initial years as a college student. Managing money, getting into fitness, learning how to cook are some skills that will drastically improve your overall life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interact with people. More experiences will add to your perspective on things which will help form your judgements. Talk to your professors, your juniors, your seniors, that one person that was in the startup that failed or the guy that was in the newspaper for his project. Increasing your perspective is important to your growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t know something, ask about it. If you don’t know you like it, try it. College is all about new experiences and getting to know yourself better. Internships will form your career experience. Intern with core as well as non-core companies [Core are those in your stream, non-core are the others].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think about ways to solve problems. Form ideas about startups and pitch them amongst a select group of friends that share your ideals. Pick an idea and work on it for 4-6 months. If it doesn’t seem fun or promising then switch ideas. &lt;strong&gt;Failure will build you up more than success ever will.&lt;/strong&gt; Understand it this way, if you have a 1% chance of success that means you are at most going to fail 99 times. This does not means that you will achieve success after 99 tries or that you need to fail 99 times to be successful. Each trial will make the next one easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Studying for some exams might end up being memorisation of boring jargon. Do it. Better to pass an exam for a course you don’t like than to give that exam again. In the long run your “KT” won’t really matter much but the toll it takes on your brain will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do not follow the herd. The first year would feel pretty chill. By the second year half of your class has some sort of certification and you are running around figuring out what to do. The third year comes and everyone is working towards their career post college. People are taking GRE, GMAT or CAT classes. It is a mess. You need to create your own roadmap. Do it. Make your plan, pivot as you learn and live your life out! &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note: Please make your own judgements regarding your career and otherwise&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>jamesfoster</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="career" /><summary type="html">The Indian engineering scene is weird. A lot of teens are forced into this line by peer and parental pressure. You may even have chosen it because you felt “this was it”. That was probably due to lack of perspective [ More on this later ]. You enter a typical engineering college and see people frantically working towards makeshift end goals that bring no joy to them in the long run. It is the assignments and the tests and that project your teacher once suggested. The cramming of formulae that are not even used to solve a mathematical question but rather to be put in your paper for that guaranteed 1 mark. The Viva where you duel with your enemy i.e the professor you foulmouthed in class or bunked their lecture in front of them a couple of times. Don’t get me wrong, if This is for you who am I to judge? However, for most students there are better careers in finance, marketing, advertising, accounting, video production, photography, music and this is just the tip of the iceberg.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/markdown.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/markdown.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">🤑 Stock investing for a baby</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/stock-investing-for-a-baby/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="🤑 Stock investing for a baby" /><published>2021-03-04T20:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2021-03-04T20:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/stock-investing-for-a-baby</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/stock-investing-for-a-baby/">&lt;p&gt;Everyone has heard of how the “share bazar” is a gamble, that trying to make money off of stocks is purely luck. They’re partly wrong and I’ll tell you why. Very broadly, when people refer to the stock market they’re either referring to Investing or Trading in Equities. Trading is like a sport, it requires a good amount of training and talent. Some are good at it, most fail at it. Not everyone is meant to run at the Olympics and here’s where most people lose their money. Where we’re going to make our money is Investing. Simply put, a trader holds and sells stocks during market hours i.e between 9:15am and 3:30pm whereas an investor holds the stock usually for more than one market day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The asset in question which is traded upon is a financial instrument - the most common of which is equity stocks. An equity stock represents a portion of a company. Imagine a company’s ownership as a cube with equity stock being its building block. As an investor, you own a portion of a company. Starting to invest in the market is easy. All you need is a savings account, a trading account, a demat account and some capital. Your savings account is held with your bank. The trading account is held with your broker (like Zerodha, Groww, Sharekhan, etc). The demat account is held with either CDSL or NDSL which are government agencies for holding dematerialised share certificates for BSE &amp;amp; NSE. With these accounts and some capital you’re more than good to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All you need to do now is pick your stock, which in and of itself is a skill you’ll learn and fine-tune over the years. While stock picking, an investor evaluates the “fundamentals” and “technicals” of the company. It’s going to be a long run learning how to invest.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[ Originally written for The Kalabhavan Express, also featured on my personal blog here ] &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Note: Please make your own judgements and do your own research while investing your money.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>jamesfoster</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="investing" /><summary type="html">Everyone has heard of how the “share bazar” is a gamble, that trying to make money off of stocks is purely luck. They’re partly wrong and I’ll tell you why. Very broadly, when people refer to the stock market they’re either referring to Investing or Trading in Equities. Trading is like a sport, it requires a good amount of training and talent. Some are good at it, most fail at it. Not everyone is meant to run at the Olympics and here’s where most people lose their money. Where we’re going to make our money is Investing. Simply put, a trader holds and sells stocks during market hours i.e between 9:15am and 3:30pm whereas an investor holds the stock usually for more than one market day.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/markdown.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/markdown.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">🏋️ How to Get up and Get in Shape</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/how-to-get-up-and-get-in-shape/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="🏋️ How to Get up and Get in Shape" /><published>2020-10-04T20:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-10-04T20:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/how-to-get-up-and-get-in-shape</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/how-to-get-up-and-get-in-shape/">&lt;p&gt;The internet, movies and television have skewed young minds into thinking that teens need to look super ripped and adults come with chiseled abs.
This is not always true. Being fit does not mean you show off your body, its just that you would love to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone has the ability to get into shape and stay there but it all comes down to you. YOU need to fuel your desire to get in shape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am going to lay down some simple keystone habits that will help you get yourself looking and feeling good. It is going to require your efforts - both Mind and Body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We start off with laying down &lt;strong&gt;a simple routine - a plan&lt;/strong&gt;. Consistently performing a set of simple exercises will show results in the long run. They would also keep you focused as you would know exactly what you need to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An example of a simple routine would be to Walk for 20 mins then performing 50 Mountain Climbers, 50 Squats and 50 Pushups. This might seem like a lot but these are rookie numbers. Split them into multiple sets. You can do 5 sets of 10 or 2 sets of 25, it is upto you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The important thing is to stay focused and disciplined and perform this routine everyday. If you have to take a day off, do not make it two. Try to increase your reps in a given set then increase the total amount of reps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your sleep is a good part of getting into shape. This is where your muscles reconstruct. Muscles grow to lift more weights by tearing down and rebuilding themselves. Although it would depend on your own body, getting about 8-9 hours of sleep should be sufficient for most people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Food is going to be key in your personal transformation. Most professionals would suggest counting calories and macros and they might be correct from their point of view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, you are just getting started and so we are going to keep it simple. Fill up your plate on protien and the rest can be carbs. We are going to focus on whole foods for protien - Beans, Dairy, Chicken, Eggs, Lentils. Check your meals for excessive fats. Having a glass of milk a day can go a long way  [about 300ml would be 8-10g of protien, check the label]. Eggs are another source of good quality protien [about 6g, google nutrition facts for the kind of egg you are consuming]. I would recommend you do your own homework with regards to the food you can consume. Control your snacking. Eat filling meals but don’t overeat too much. A banana roughly 15 mins before working out will help keep your energy levels right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do not look at super ripped people in the movies, on tv shows or on the internet. There is a reason normal gym goers or people that consistently workout do not look like that. We are looking at a sustainable way to get into shape and maintain it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the long run, invest in some good jump rope and dumbells. These items have a sufficiently good ROI for you to spend your money on, if you use them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Possibly stay away from supplementing with protien. If you are not in shape right now it is the fault of your eating habits and workout habits. We need to fix them before we try to boost them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consistency, Discipline and having a plan will go a long way in getting you fitter.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: Adjust this to you own health and dietary needs.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>jamesfoster</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="health" /><category term="fitness" /><summary type="html">The internet, movies and television have skewed young minds into thinking that teens need to look super ripped and adults come with chiseled abs. This is not always true. Being fit does not mean you show off your body, its just that you would love to.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/markdown.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/markdown.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>